Guide to the Karl Ichiro Akiya Papers TAM.236
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Karl Ichiro Akiya Papers
1921-2002
1949-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Akiya, Karl Ichiro, 1909-2001
Chestnut, Elizabeth Akiya
Akiya, Frederick
TAM.236
10 Linear Feet in 7 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, 3 oversized flat boxes, and 1 oversize folder.
Karl Ichiro Akiya (1909-2001) was an activist in the labor and Japanese community both in the United States and Japan. Incarcerated at the Topaz War Relocation Center in Topaz, Utah, he was released to serve as a language instructor in the U.S. Army's Japanese language school at the University of Michigan. Akiya was member of the Japanese American Citizens League, the Furniture Workers Union and the Communist Party of the U.S.A. He wrote for the Japanese American Hokubei Shimpo and literary magazine the New York Bungei. The collection contains subject files documenting Akiya's life and work in the United States and Japan; his writings, including articles published in Hokubei Shimpo newspaper and The New York Bungei, essays, short novels, and an autobiography; notebooks and address books; artwork and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Karl Ichiro Akiya Papers were given to the Tamiment Library by Elizabeth Chestnut Akiya and Frederick Akiya in 2002. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2002.007 and 2017.074.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Subject Files, 1937-2002
Writings, 1921-1999
Notebooks, 1942-1997
Artwork and Photographs, 1942-1990
Oversize and Ephemera, 1949-1987
Biographical Note
Labor and community activist Karl Ichiro Akiya (1909-2001) was born in San Francisco but at the age of six, sent to be educated in Japan. In 1927 he entered Kwansei Gakuin University (also known as Kansei Gakuin Daigaku), a Methodist school, for preparation in secondary school teaching where he studied Japanese and English language literature. During these years, Akiya fully immersed himself in extracurricular student life. He converted to the Methodist faith, was elected class chairman and participated in the movements opposing compulsory military training for college students and the increasing militarization of Japan. His political activities brought him into association with the union movement and the Japanese Socialist and Communist Parties. He became a member of the Communist Party and changed his first name to Karl after Karl Marx.
After graduating college in 1932, Akiya returned to the United States to avoid being drafted into the Japanese Army. Having moved to San Francisco, where is father operated a hotel, Akiya landed his first job as a staff writer for the Japanese North American daily Nichibei Times. He later worked for the San Francisco branch of the Sumitomo Bank. In his spare hours, Akiya continued his activist work, joining the Japanese American Citizens League, which was becoming active in the fight against racial discrimination. In the late 1930s, he worked at recruiting Asian Americans as an organizer for the Congress of Industrial Organizations and National Maritime Union. He also joined the U.S. Communist Party.
Following Japan's attack on Pearl Harbor, Akiya was incarcerated at the Topaz War Relocation Center in Topaz, Utah. He was released shortly thereafter and recruited to serve as a language instructor at the University of Michigan's Japanese language school run by the U.S. Army. In 1944, he married fellow instructor Satoko Murakami.
In 1946, the Akiyas, with daughter Elizabeth in tow, settled in New York's Lower East Side. There, on February 20, 1947, the couple's second child Fred was born. In New York, Akiya pursued a profession as a furniture finisher and also joined the Furniture Workers Union. From 1954 until 1980, Akiya worked for the Bank of Tokyo in New York City. In addition to his communist-affiliated activities, Akiya was extremely active in the civil rights, peace, and anti-nuclear movements. In 1987, his efforts were formally recognized when he was honored as recipient of the Martin Luther King, Jr. Award for Community Organizing for his work with African American youths in Harlem and Chinese and Korean immigrant workers.
In addition to community work, Akiya wrote prolifically. His writings include articles published in Hokubei Shimpo newspaper and The New York Bungei, a literary magazine he helped found in 1959; essays; short novels, and an autobiography.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Roger Hargrave Scrapbooks (ALBA 245)
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Subject Files, 1937-2002 contains correspondence, manuscript material and newspaper clippings documenting Akiya's life and work both in the United States and Japan. Materials describing his education at Kwansei Gakuin University, his incarceration at Camp Topaz, and his work in World War II for the United States government at the University of Michigan and with the Office of Strategic Services are present. His political work in the civil rights and anti-war movement is documented, as is his involvement in the campaign for nuclear disarmament and his efforts to commemorate the victims of the atomic bombing of Hiroshima and Nagasaki. Also present are materials relating to Akiya's work in the Japanese American Redress movement. Materials documenting Akiya's ongoing interest in Japanese and Japanese American language and literature, including correspondence with Japanese and Japanese American artists, writers and politicians are also included. Also present are materials related to his work for Japanese American newspapers the Nichibei Times, New York Bungei and Hokubei Shimpo. Also included in this series are files relating to his family (wife and children), including correspondence and personal records.
Series II: Writings, 1921-1999 includes Akiya's 1994 autobiography (in Japanese and English), a weekly journal written in elementary school, college essays on religion, short novels written in the 1950s, some for the Hokubei Shimpo; an essay on his incarceration at the Topaz War Relocation Center, a concentration camp euphemistically referred to as an relocation or internment camp, and miscellaneous essays on linguistics and the labor and student movements. A draft of his novel "The Little Champion" is also included.
Series III: Notebooks, 1942-1997 contains address books and small notebooks containing contact information, notes and lists. Also included are Akiya's diaries from 1942 and 1994 through 1998. The bank savings books of Akiya and his family are also present.
Series IV: Artwork and Photographs, 1942-1990 includes artwork, photographic prints and negatives relating to the movement to ban the atomic bomb, the Topaz concentration camp, and Kwansei Gakuin University. Examples of Akiya's calligraphy are also included, as are his drawings from a correspondence class with the Washington School of Art. Also present is a color photocopy of a photo album documenting Akiya's work at the University of Michigan's Japanese Language School.
Series V: Oversize and Ephemera, 1949-1987 includes realia, memorabilia, oversize photographs and three videos. The bulk of this series consists of memorabilia from Kwansei Gakuin University, including banners, spoons, and awards. Other items include oversize photographs from the Bank of Tokyo Christmas Party and Annual Picnic, as well as Akiya's wallet and identification cards. Of particular significance is a box containing broken glass and rock from the "Peekskill Riots" of 1949 and a Roger Hargrave Scrapbook from the Spanish Civil War.
Separated Materials
About one hundred books and serials have separated to the Fales Library from the collection.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Correspondence.; Artifacts (object genre); Calligraphy (visual works); New York (N.Y.).; Videocassettes.; Memorabilia.; Japanese American literature.; Japanese American communists.; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Japanese American newspapers.; Japanese American artists.; Communists -- United States.; Japanese Americans -- Civil rights; Black-and-white photographs.; Japanese American authors.; Manuscripts; Clippings (information artifacts); Motion pictures |z Japan.; Motion pictures, American |z Japan.; Japanese Americans -- Reparations.; Topaz (Utah); Nihon Kyōsantō; National Rainbow Coalition (U.S.); New York Bungei; United States. Office of Strategic Services; U.S.ENGLISH (Organization); Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Tōkyō Ginkō; Sunami, Soichi, 1885-1971; Shirai, Jakku, 1900?-1937; Shibata, Shingo, 1930-; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Kansei Gakuin Daigaku; Japanese American Citizens' League; Japanese American United Church; Japanese American Social Services, Inc.; Ariyoshi, Sawako, 1931-1984; Akiya, Satoko.; Abe, Yoshio; Okubo, Miné; Kawakami, Tamio, 1925-; Ishigaki, Ayako, 1903-; Hayashi, Tetsumaro; Franklin Delano Roosevelt Memorial Commission; Communist Party of the United States of America; Chinese Progressive Association (San Francisco, Calif.); Central Utah Relocation Center; Association of Black Social Workers; Yoneda, Karl G., 1906-; Tamotsu, Chūzō, 1888-1975; Japanese American Help for the Aging, Inc.; Japanese American Association of New York; Inoue Chamber Ensemble; Hokubei Shimpo; Heart Mountain Relocation Center (Wyo.); Chestnut, Elizabeth Akiya; Akiya, Frederick
- Series I: Subject Files, 1937-2002.
  - Abe, Yoshio (poet): Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Akiya, Hama and Sadataro (parents of Karl Akiya): Death Certificates and Documents, 1964-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Akiya, Matsuko (4th wife): Medicare Insurance, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Akiya, Matsuko: Personal Documents, 1972-1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Akiya, Satoko: Correspondence, 1945-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Akiya, Satoko: Correspondence and Lists (Beekman Downtown Hospital), 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Akiya, Satoko: Correspondence with Karl Akiya, 1945-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Akiya, Satoko: Medical Records, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Akiya, Satoko: Memorial Service and Condolence Cards, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Akiya, Satoko: Writings, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Anti-Black Racism: Clippings, Press Release, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Apartheid, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Apartment Lease and Insurance, 1954-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ariyoshi, Sawako: Correspondence, 1960-1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Army Japanese Language School Reunion, Aug 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Asian Pacific American Community Organizations and Resources, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Association of Black Social Workers Senior Center, 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Atomic Bomb: Clippings, Correspondence, Writings, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bank of Tokyo: Press Releases, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bank of Tokyo: Statements, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Biographical Material, 1980-2002 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Book Index, 1991-2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Book Index (photocopy), 1991-2002 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Book List (books donated to Fales Library, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bridges, Harry (National Maritime Union): Clippings, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Chestnut, Elizabeth (daughter): Correspondence, 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Chestnut, Elizabeth (daughter): Family Photos (photocopies), Clippings and Notes, 1970-1996 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Chinese American Community: Chinese Progressive Association, Vincent Chin Case, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Chorus City (musical group): Clippings and Programs, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Civil Rights: Clippings, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Civil Rights: Clippings, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Civil Rights: Clippings, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Clippings, 1947-1956 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Clippings, 1958-1974 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Clippings, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings: Ethnic Issues, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings: Ethnic Issues, 1981-1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Hospice, Middle East, France, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Communist Party of the USA: Articles, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Autobiography, 1994-1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Holiday Cards, 1945-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: to Akiya, 1957-1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: to and from Akiya, 1942-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Films (American): Clippings, 1951-1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Films (Japanese): Clippings, 1952-1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Films (Japanese American): Clippings, 1955-1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Financial Documents, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Franklin Delano Roosevelt Memorial Commission: Founding Member Certificate, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Grenada Invasion: Statements, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Guernica (Picasso painting): Clippings, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hayashi, Tetsumaro (writer): Correspondence and Clippings, 1972-1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Heart Mountain (concentration camp): Photo Exhibit, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hitler, Adolf: Mein Kampf (published in newspaper format), 1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Hokubei Shimpo, 1945-1959 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Hokubei Shimpo, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Hokubei Shimpo: Articles by Karl Yoneda, Senryu poems, 1945-1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Immigrant Associations and Organizations, 1982-1992 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Inoue Chamber Ensemble: Hiroshima/Nagasaki Commemorative Concerts, 1985-1987, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Ishigaki, Ayako (activist and author): Clippings and Correspondence, 1968-1987 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Japan Correspondence (column by Masao Matsumoto) (I), 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Japan Correspondence (column by Masao Matsumoto) (II), 1949-1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Japan Correspondence (column by Masao Matsumoto) (III), 1959-1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Japan Trips, 1973-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Japanese American Artists, 1946-1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Japanese American Association of New York, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Japanese American Citizens League: The New York Scene (newsletter), 1974-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Japanese American Counseling Center, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Japanese American First Generation (Issei): Clippings, 1988-1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Japanese American Help for the Aging, Inc (JAHFA): Newsletters, 1976-1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Japanese American Musicians: Clippings and Programs, 1946-1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Japanese American News Corp: Correspondence, 1946-1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Japanese American Performance Art: Clippings and Playbills, 1950-1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Japanese American Social Services, Inc (JASSI): Newsletters, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Japanese American United Church, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Japanese American United Church: Tom Hayashi Memorial Vault (Satoko Akiya's interment), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Japanese Americans: Clippings (Hokubei Mainichi, New York Nichibei News), 1952-1986 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Japanese Artists: Clippings, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Japanese Celebrities: Clippings, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Japanese Celebrities: Clippings, 1981-1995 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Japanese Communist Party: Clippings and Correspondence, 1945-1962 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Japanese Communist Party: Clippings and Correspondence, 1975-1984 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Japanese Communist Party: Clippings and Correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Japanese Communist Party: Satomi Hakamada Case, 1971-1979 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Japanese Culture: Songsheets, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Japanese History: Clippings (One Hundred Years of Japanese History series, Yomiuri News), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Japanese Literature: Angel's Death (periodical), 1937 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Japanese Literature: Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Japanese Literature: Reader's Digest Clippings, 1961-1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Japanese Literature: Reader's Digest Clippings, 1981-1995 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Japanese Literature: Senryu Poems, 1938-1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Japanese Period Drama: Clippings, 1990-1996 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Kawakami, Tamio (Japanese politician): Correspondence, 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Kwansei Gakuin University (Kansei Gakuin Daigaku), 1928-1996 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Kwansei Gakuin University (Kansei Gakuin Daigaku) Alumni Association: Correspondence, 1964-1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Kwansei Gakuin University (Kansei Gakuin Daigaku): Clippings, 1940-1998 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Kwansei Gakuin University (Kansei Gakuin Daigaku): Correspondence with Alumni and Associations, 1976-1988 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Kwansei Gakuin University (Kansei Gakuin Daigaku): Correspondence with Alumni and Associations, 1989-1998 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Kwansei Gakuin University (Kansei Gakuin Daigaku): Memorial for Kitano Daikichi, 1969-1996 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Kwansei Gakuin University (Kansei Gakuin Daigaku): Newsletter, 1988-1999 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Linguistics: Japanese, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Linguistics: "Roots of Words" Clippings (column), 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Marxist-Leninist Literature, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Medical Expenses and Records (Prudential AARP Insurance), 1996 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - New York Anti-Apartheid Coordinating Council, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - New York Bungei: Clippings, 1947-1961 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - New York Bungei: Clippings, 1962-1986 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - New York Bungei: Correspondence with Publisher in Japan, 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - New York Bungei: "Twelve Years History of New York Bungei", 1967 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - New York City Housing Authority: St. Mary's Park Houses Application, 1958-1971 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - New York City: Resources, 1978-1986 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - New York Community Redress Celebration, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - New York Politics, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Nichibei Times: "California Documentary" (column), 1987 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Nichibei Times: "California Documentary" (column), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Nipponzan Myohoji (Peace Pagoda): Correspondence and Newsletters, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Obituaries (I), 1947-1998 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Obituaries (II), 1973-1994 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - OCS News (Ornithological Journal): Clippings, 1992-1996 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Okubo, Mine (artist): Clippings, Correspondence and Programs, 1972-2001 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Philippines, 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Politics: Clippings, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Politics: Clippings, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Politics: Clippings, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Political Activities, 1979-1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Rainbow Coalition: Presidential Elections (Jesse Jackson), 1984-1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Redress, 1971-1995 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Redress: Clippings, 1978-1993 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Restaurant Information (New York City), 1970 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Retiree Club of Pan Am Northeastern Area, Inc, 1977-1996 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Robeson, Paul: Clippings, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Rosenberg Case, 1975-1988 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Shibata, Shingo (Professor, Hiroshima University): Articles, 1975-1999 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Shirai, Jack (Spanish Civil War Veteran): Flyer, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Sooka Gakkai (religious organization): Notes, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Soviet Union: News Clippings, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Statement of United States Citizen of Japanese Ancestry, circa 1942 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Sunami, Soichi (photographer): Correspondence, 1971-1981 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Tamotzu, Chuzo (artist): Correspondence with Louise Tamotzu, Programs, 1981-1986 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Tax Documents, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Theater: Clippings, 1942-1950 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Topaz (Concentration Camp): Correspondence and Clippings, 1941-1944 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Topaz (Concentration Camp): Correspondence with Sandra Taylor (University of Utah) re: Jewel of the Desert (book), 1984-1993 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - United Farm Workers of America, 1983-1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - U.S. English (organization): Correspondence and Clippings, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "U.S Foreign Policy and the World Today" (interview with Mae Ngai), 1986 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - West Coast Japanese American Community, 1973-1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - World Economy: Clippings, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - World Literature: Clippings, 1972-1981 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - World War II: Clippings, 1990-1999 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Yamada, Mikio (writer): Correspondence, 1978-1996 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Yamanaka, Michiko (writer): Correspondence and Clippings, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Yoneda, Karl and Elaine: Clippings and Writings, 1973-1986 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Yoshida, Takashi: "Standing Loyally by the Flag: The Experience of People of Japanese Ancestry in New York" (typescript), 1997 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Series II: Writings, 1921-1999
  - Autobiography (English): Chapters 1-30 (manuscript), 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Autobiography (English): Chapters 31-39 (manuscript), 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Autobiography (Japanese): Chapters 1-39 (manuscript), 1994 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Autobiography (Japanese): Chapters 1-39 (typescript), 1995 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Autobiography: Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Essays, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Essays: College Essays, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Essays: Ideology and Materialism, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Essays: Labor and Student Movements, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Essays: Linguistics and Education, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Essays: Topaz Concentration Camp (Paul Robeson), undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Linguistics Bibliography, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Notes and Lists, 1968-1985 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Novel: "The Little Champion" (draft), 1951 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Short Novel: Draft, 1950-1959 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Short Novels: A Week When the Painting Disappears, Heating Sand and Black Rain (photocopies), 1950-1959 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Short Novels: Manuscripts for Hokubei Shimpo, 1950-1959 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Weekly Journal (Elementary and Junior High School), 1921-1926 (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Series III: Notebooks, 1942-1997
  - Address Books, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Address Book and Notebook, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Diary, Jan 1, 1994-Feb 10, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Diary, Feb 11, 1995-Nov 4, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Diary, Nov 15, 1995-Sep 4, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Diary, Sep 5, 1996-Jul 19, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Diary, Jul 20, 1997-Jul 28, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Savings Books, 1962-1983 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Notebooks, undated, 1993-1996 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Artwork and Photographs, 1942-1990
  - Artwork: Calligraphy, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Artwork: Concentration Camp (negatives), 1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Artwork: Concentration Camp (photos), 1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Artwork: Concentration Camp (slides), undated (Box 8, Folder 4)